Roger Wolcott Papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Roger Wolcott Papers
1631-1889
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Wolcott, Roger
1.5 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, promissory notes, papers concerning the Spanish ship case and papers about trouble in the Second Church in Windsor.
Biographical Sketch
Roger Wolcott was born in Windsor, Connecticut on January 4, 1679, the youngest son of Simon and Martha (Pitkin) Wolcott. He was apprenticed to a clothier in 1694 and left five years later to set up a successful business of his own. On December 3, 1702, he married Sarah Drake (1684?-1748) the daughter of Sgt. Job and Mary (Wolcott) Drake.
Wolcott's public career began in 1707 when he was chosen a selectman of the town of Windsor. Two years later, in May 1709, he was admitted to practice at the bar. He served as a Representative of South Windsor in the Connecticut General Assembly in 1709, was raised to the bench of justices in 1710, was elected member of Council in 1714, Judge of the County Court in 1724, and Judge of the Superior Court in 1732. In 1741 he was named Chief Justice of the Supreme Court and Deputy Governor. He was elected Governor in 1750, a position he held for four years.
Wolcott was appointed Commissary of the Connecticut Forces in the 1711 expedition against Canada in Queen Anne's War (the War of Spanish Succession, 1702-1713). In 1745, at the age of 66, Wolcott was commissioned Major General by Governor William Shirley of Massachusetts and was second in command to Sir William Pepperell in the expedition against Louisbourg during King George's War (the War of the Austrian Succession, 1744-1748).
Wolcott kept a journal during the Louisbourg expedition which was printed in the Connecticut Historical Society's Collections, Volumes XVI and XVII. He was the author of one of the earliest volumes of poetry printed in Connecticut, Poetical Meditations being the Improvement of some Vacant Hours. He also published a small quarto, A Letter to the Reverend Mr. Noah Hobart. In 1895, the Connecticut Historical Society published, as part of the third volume of its Collections, A Memoir for the History of Connecticut, By Roger Wolcott, 1759, from the original manuscript in possession of the Watkinson Library in Hartford.
Roger and Sarah Wolcott had fifteen children, including Oliver, a governor of Connecticut and signer of the Declaration of Independence. Roger Wolcott died May 17, 1767, and is buried in Windsor Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence to and from Roger Wolcott, financial papers, legal papers, diaries and literary papers with transcriptions. The correspondence also includes some early 17th century Wolcott family letters.
Arrangement
Materials are organized into three series: Correspondence, Diaries, and Literary Papers.
Series I: Correspondence consists of Wolcott family letters, including Henry Wolcott, Josiah Wolcott, Oliver Wolcott, Sr., Sarah Chauncy, and Matthew Allyn, and letters to and from Roger Wolcott. The letters concern relations with Native Americans, military, legal, political, and religious matters, and material concerning the Spanish ship case.
Series II: Diaries contains an original diary and two transcriptions.
Series III: Literary Papers comprises a manuscript and transcription of narrative of the troubles in the Second Church in Windsor between 1735-1741
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection. When material is fragile, researcher may be directed to microfilm copies.
Accruals
The collection is open, but additional material is not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Wolcott, Henry, 1643-1709.; Wolcott, Oliver, 1726-1797.; Chauncey, Sarah Wolcott.; Allyn, Matthew, d. 1758.
Subjects
Indians of North America.
Geographic Names
Connecticut Politics and government Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; United States History King George's War, 1744-1748.
Genre Forms
Holographs; holographs, signed.
Contents:
- I. Correspondence
  - Letters to, from, and concerning Wolcott family members, including Henry Wolcott and Josiah Wolcott, 1631-1693; (22 items) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters primarily to Henry Wolcott, 1695-1702; (23 items) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to, from, and concerning Wolcott family members, including Matthew Allyn, Sarah Chauncey, and Roger Wolcott. Account list for the Connecticut Colony, 1730., 1703-1742; (18 items) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Roger Wolcott, petitions, accounts, Roger Wolcott's commission from William Shirley, 1743-1744; (11 items) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to, from, and concerning Roger Wolcott, 1745; (25 items) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters primarily to Roger Wolcott, 1746; (17 items) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters primarily to Roger Wolcott, 1747; (12 items) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters primarily to Roger Wolcott, 1748-1749; (9 items) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to and from Roger Wolcott; bills of exchange, 1750; (11 items) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to and from Roger Wolcott; petitions, 1751; (10 items) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to and from Roger Wolcott; resolutions of the Consociation Meeting of Churches within the County of Litchfield, 1752; (13 items) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to and from Roger Wolcott, 1753-1754; (19 items) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters primarily to and from Roger Wolcott; letter from Oliver Wolcott; enlistment of Price Abbot, 1754; (9 items) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, manifests, will and testament of Henry Wolcott with testimony of Roger Wolcott; printed page from The Citizen (April 27, 1889); list of letters to Henry Wolcott, 1753-1889; (10 items) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Orders, lists of governors, legal statements, accounts of ships' merchandise, depositions, and letters in Spanish and English, 1749-1752; (20 items) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters and legal documents concerning the Spanish ship case, one in Spanish, 1752; (8 items) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, promissory notes, and documents concerning the Spanish ship case, January - June, 1753; (19 items) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Declaration in 18 pages of Joseph Miguel de San Juan regarding the Spanish ship case, 1753; (1 items) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters to and from Roger Wolcott, two in Spanish, June - August,1753; (17 items) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters to and from Roger Wolcott concerning the Spanish ship case, September - December,1753; (12 items) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters and documents concerning the Spanish ship case, January, 1754; (7 items) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters and documents concerning the Spanish ship case, October, 1754; (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters and documents concerning the Spanish ship case, November, 1754; (18 items) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters and documents concerning the Spanish ship case, December, 1754; (22 items) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters and documents concerning the Spanish ship case, two in Spanish, January, 1755; (18 items) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters concerning the Spanish ship case, one in French, October - December, 1755; (4 items) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters to and from Roger Wolcott and concerning the Spanish ship case; printed extract; proclamation (copy), 1756-1766; (11 items) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Typewritten carbon copies of letters from Roger Wolcott; typed carbon copy of Power of Attorney, Joseph Drake to Ezakiah Bliss; list of important dates in Roger Wolcott's life, 1728-1748; (12 items) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- II. Diaries
  - Major General Roger Wolcott's Diary of the Siege of Louisbourg, 1745, Together with his Autobiography and Religious Reflections, transcribed by Doris E. Cook[between 1969-1974], 1747-1755; (1 (30 pp) items) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Roger Wolcott's Diary of the Siege of Louisbourg in 1745, together with his Autobiography and Religious Reflections. Transcribed by Henry Stevens, Jr., 1845, (1 (58 pp) items) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Roger Wolcott's Journal, 1745-1755; (1 items) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- III. Literary Papers
  - Roger Wolcott's A Narrative of the Troubles in the Second Church in Windsor from the Year 1735 to the Year 1741...Transcribed by Doris Cook [between 1969 and 1974], (1 (55 pp) items) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Roger Wolcott's A Narrative of the Troubles in the Second Church in Windsor from the Year 1735 to the Year 1741, (1 items) (Box 3, Folder 6)